Continuing our investigation of benchmarks, and this will become more real when we actually see some
벤치마크를 계속 조사할 겁니다 실제로 행동을 보면 더 실감이 날 거예요
action.
그러니 참고 들으세요 아주 중요하고 유용한 배경 정보니까요
We're going to look at three specific benchmarks used to test, uh, more, more, uh, specialized
더 특별한 기술을 시험할 때 사용되는 세 가지 벤치마크를 살펴볼
skills.
거예요
And the first of them is is used for evaluating chat between models, um, particularly in the in face
첫 번째는 모델들 간의 채팅을 평가하는 데 사용해요 특히 인 페이스오프에서요
offs between models in things like arenas, as we will see.
아레나 같은 곳에서요
And the benchmark is an Elo rating.
평가 기준은 Elo예요
Uh, if you are a chess player or familiar with with chess Elo ratings, Elo is a rating that you can
체스 선수라면 Elo 평가라는 게 있는데 Elo는 다른 스포츠의
give to competitors in a sport or some sort of a game where there is a loser for every winner, where
경쟁자들에게 주는 평가예요 승자마다 패자가 있는 제로 섬 게임이죠
it's a zero sum game, um, and uh, uh, based on the outcomes of these kinds of, of games, uh,
이런 게임의 결과에 따라 사람들에게 체력에 영향을 주는
you can give people this relative measure that affects their strength compared to others based on their
상대적인 척도를 줄 수 있어요 헤드 투 헤드 대결의 성적을 토대로요
So you'll see examples of of those from an arena later and that will that will bring it to life.
나중에 아레나에서 예제를 보여드릴 텐데 그럼 활기가 생기죠
Um, but it's a, it's used in particular the ones that I'm going to show you are used to evaluate the
제가 보여드릴 이 모듈은 채팅 기능을 평가할 때 사용됩니다
chat abilities, the instruct abilities of these models.
이 모델의 지시 기능을 평가할 때요
And then the next two are about coding.
다음 두 개는 코딩에 관한 거예요
Human eval is a very well known Python coding test.
인간 평가는 파이썬 코딩 테스트로 아주 유명하죠
It's 164 problems.
164개예요
Uh, it's about writing code actually based on Python doc strings.
파이썬 문서 문자열에 기반한 코드 작성하기예요
Uh, and it's something where models have become increasingly effective at and then, uh, multiple
이런 모델은 점점 더 효과적으로 변하고 있습니다. 여러 번이라고 발음할 수도
or maybe it's pronounced multiple.
있겠네요.
Uh, I expect just multiple is the same thing, but translated to 18 different programming languages.
여러 개라는 건 같은 거지만 18개의 다른 프로그래밍 언어로 번역된 거죠
So this is more of a wider variety of programming skills across different areas.
다양한 영역에 걸친 프로그래밍 기술이 더 폭넓게 사용되는 거죠
Let me take a moment now to mention Mentioned the limitations of these benchmarks, which is such an
잠시 언급할 게 있어요 이런 벤치마크의 한계를요 아주 중요한 점이죠
important point, and it's something that that cannot be stressed enough.
아무리 강조해도 지나치지 않아요
Benchmarks are useful for us for comparing, of course, the different where different models shine
벤치마크는 비교에 유용합니다 각 모델이 돋보이는 부분과 사용 의도가
and where they're not not intended to be used.
아닌 부분을 비교하죠
But there are problems with benchmarks, and you need to be aware of them when you look at them.
하지만 벤치마크에는 문제가 있어요 그걸 볼 때 인식해야 하죠
One of them is that they are not consistently applied.
그 중 하나는 일관되게 적용되지 않는다는 거죠
So, um, depending on where you're seeing the benchmark, particularly if it's something like a press
기준점이 어디인지에 따라 달라요 특히 회사의 언론 자료라면
release from a company, they it's really up to them how they measured the benchmark, what kind of
기준점을 어떻게 측정했는지 어떤 하드웨어를 사용했는지 그런 건 해당
hardware they used and stuff like that.
기업에 달렸죠
It's not like there's a gold standards that, that, um, put these measurements on rails.
Let's go 금 기준이 있는 것도 아니고 레일에 치수를 재는 것도 아니잖아요
So everything has to be taken with a pinch of salt.
그러니 모든 걸 염두에 둬야 해요
If it's been published by a third party, there can be too narrow in scope, particularly when you think
타사에 의해 게시된 경우 그 범위가 너무 좁을 수 있어요 특히 객관식 스타일
about like multiple choice style questions and a very similar point.
문제 같은 경우에요 아주 유사한 관점이죠
Uh, it's hard to use these kinds of benchmarks to measure nuanced reasoning if you're dealing with
이런 벤치마크를 이용해 뉘앙스를 측정하는 건 어렵죠 객관식이나
with either multiple choice or very specific kinds of answers, it's that that's something that's hard
아주 특정한 답을 다루는 문제라면요 그건 정말 어려운 일이에요
Um, another problem is training data leakage, which it's just very hard to make sure that there is
또 다른 문제는 훈련 데이터 유출인데 확신하기 어렵습니다 훈련에 사용되는
no way that any of these answers can be found within the data that's used to train models, particularly
데이터에서 이런 해답을 찾을 방법이 없다는 것을요 특히 모델이 최근 데이터로 훈련될수록
as models get trained with more and more recent data that presumably involves lots of information about
이런 기준점에 관한 많은 정보가 포함될 테니까요
Uh, it becomes harder and harder to control for training data leakage.
훈련 데이터 유출을 통제하기가 점점 더 어려워져요
And then the next one here is is a very important overfitting, a common term from traditional data
다음은 아주 중요한 과잉 설정입니다 전통적인 데이터 과학에서 흔히 쓰이는
science.
용어죠
The problem is and this is this is a bit subtle.
문제는 비트가 좀 미묘하다는 거예요
Again you could get to a point where you've managed to make your model do really, really well on benchmarks,
벤치 마크에서 모델을 정말 정말 잘 만들도록 관리하는 지점에 도달할 수 있습니다 부분적으로 많은 걸 시도해
partly because you've just tried out lots of things, like you've tweaked lots of hyperparameters,
봤기 때문이죠 많은 hyperpaameter를 변경한 것처럼요 모델과
lots of the sort of settings around a model, and you've kept rerunning it until you've tweaked all
관련된 많은 종류의 설정들이요 모든 hyperpaameter를 변경할 때까지
the hyperparameters, and now it's crushing this particular benchmark.
계속 다시 실행해 이제 이 벤치 마크를 박살내고 있어요
and it might be something of a coincidence.
우연의 일치일 수도 있어요
It's like you've because you've had all of these different knobs that you've you've turned you've turned
다양한 노브들이 있기 때문에 특정 방식으로
them specifically in such a way that it solves these benchmarks really, really well.
돌려서 벤치마크를 아주 잘 해결한 거죠
And what's the problem with that?
그게 뭐가 문제죠?
The problem with that is that you've just solved for this particular benchmark test.
문제는 이 특정 기준 테스트에 대해 방금 해결했다는 거죠
And if you ask another question, which is still trying to get to the heart of the same test, but it's
다른 질문을 할 때 같은 테스트의 핵심을 전달하려고 하지만 질문이
just asked differently, or it's just a, you know, a different maths question or something like that,
다르거나 수학이 다른 질문일 경우 모델이 대폭 실패할 수 있어요
the model might fail spectacularly because you've overfit it, you've trained it, you've, you've,
너무 완벽해서죠 훈련시키고 다양한 채널을 설정해서 특정 벤치마크
you've, you've, you've set all of its various dials so that it does really, really well on these
문제에서 잘 작동하게 했어요 하지만 샘플에서
very specific benchmark questions and doesn't do so well when it goes out of sample, when it goes out
나올 때는 잘 작동하지 않죠 벤치마크 문제에서 다른 질문으로 나갈 때는
of these benchmarks, questions to other questions designed to test the same kind of thing.
같은 걸 테스트하도록 설계됐어요
In other words, the results of the benchmark can end up being misleading.
다시 말해 기준 결과가 오도될 수 있다는 거죠
It can make it look like it's really good at Python coding or at maths problems or something like that,
파이썬 코딩이나 수학 문제에 아주 잘 맞는 것처럼 보이게 할 수 있습니다
when really it's just really good at answering the specific questions that were in these benchmarks.
벤치마크에 있는 특정 질문에 대한 답변을 아주 잘 하는 것처럼 보일 수도 있어요
So that's the problem of overfitting.
그게 과잉복지의 문제예요
It's very important that you're aware of that and take some healthy skepticism to reviewing benchmarks
이를 인지하고 벤치마크를 검토하는 건전한 회의론을 갖는 것이 매우
with this in mind.
중요해요
There is a new interesting point that's been raised recently, which isn't yet proven.
최근에 새로운 흥미로운 관점이 제기됐는데 아직 증명되진 않았어요
It's not yet well understood.
아직 잘 이해되지 않았어요
It's still a bit speculative, but there is some evidence that the latest frontier models, the really
아직은 추측이지만 최신 프론티어 모델인 GPT 4 클로드
strong GPT four Claude 3.5 sonnet level models have some kind of awareness that they are being evaluated,
3이 비트코인이라는 증거가 있어요 5개의 소네트 수준 모델은 자신이 평가받는다는 걸 어느 정도
that when they are being asked various benchmark style questions, and that some of their answers have
인지하고 있습니다 다양한 기준이 되는 질문을 받을 때 그들의 답변은 그들이 전후 사정을
indicated to experts that they are aware of the context, that they're being asked this because they
알고 있다는 걸 나타내죠 그들이 이런 질문을 받는 건 평가받고 있기 때문이에요
Um, and that might distort some of their answers.
그러면 일부 답변이 왜곡될 수 있어요
Now, you may wonder, why does that matter if we're testing things like how good they are at maths.
수학을 얼마나 잘하는지 테스트하는 건데 그게 왜 중요한지 궁금하실 거예요
Whether they know they're being evaluated or not doesn't matter.
그들이 평가받는다는 걸 알든 모르든 상관없어요
That's sure they can know they're being evaluated.
평가받는다는 걸 알 수 있겠죠
And still, whether they do well or not in maths questions is is useful.
수학 문제를 잘 푸는지 못 푸는지가 중요하죠
Well, here's an example of where it matters.
중요한 게 뭔지 보여드리죠
Supposing you're asking questions about things like safety and alignment, and some of the questions
안전과 정렬에 관한 질문을 한다고 가정해 보죠 적대적인 상황에서 진실하게
we saw about responding truthfully in adversarial conditions.
대응하는 것에 관한 질문도요
If that's what you're trying to assess, then obviously if the model is aware that it's being assessed,
그걸 평가하려는 거라면 모델이 평가되고 있다는 걸 인식한다면 그 질문에
that might change its approach to answering those questions.
대한 답변에 대한 접근 방식이 바뀔 수도 있죠
And perhaps, for example, give an impression that a model is highly truthful or well aligned, when
예를 들어 모델이 매우 진실하거나 정렬이 잘 맞는 것처럼 보이게 하는 거죠 실제로는 그렇지
in fact it is not.
않은데도요
So it's premature for us to say that this is a real concern or a real problem.
따라서 이것이 진짜 문제라고 단정 짓기엔 시기상조죠
It's it's a it's a it's a risk that people are analysing and researching not yet known if it is a real
아직은 실제 문제인지 알 수 없지만 사람들이 분석하고 연구하고 있는 위험 요소예요
problem, but at this point, it certainly is something that's a concern that's being explored.
하지만 현재로서는 확실히 고려하고 있는 문제죠
All right.
좋아요
Hope that was interesting to you.
그게 흥미로웠길 바라요
This gives you some of the limitations of benchmarks.
벤치마크의 한계를 보여 주죠
And now we're going to move on to some more.
이제 다음 단계로 넘어가죠